[SPEAKER_01]: What would you say are the requirements for somebody who tries to practice towards Right View in the lay environment with all its responsibilities and duties that it comes with?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, first of all, try to minimize those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, keep the precepts, first of all, including celibacy, if you're actually serious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh... see, you wouldn't be doing that if you had been... if you had developed the connection of what suffering is, what delight is, how your own actions influence it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, for as long as you keep that there, and any action that is obviously rooted in craving and in wholesome states, you're maintaining your non-seeing of craving as an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you abstractly recognize, oh, yeah, you know, monks are practicing the ideal way, because they are giving these things up for you internally, this is not felt as a problem, and that's what the wrong view is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just like theoretical, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise, anybody who just thinks about, like, changes their opinions externally, can just become a sotāpanna overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha wouldn't say how unique and how amazing it is for somebody to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you basically, yeah, cut out those things that are obviously against the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, let's say, those other responsibilities you have that are left after you have... Because, you see, many of those responsibilities and duties and engagements are there only because of these things that you haven't given up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unnecessary things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you remove those, you're going to be left with the things that are actually neutral, in terms of, like, the intention why you're doing them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, within that, you can start to... Well, obviously, there's always going to be some level of your own input.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't have the perfect environment that prevents you from acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always going to be a possibility for you to take things up wrongly, even within the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you can start to have, let's say, a similar level of self-questioning as to, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to have to be, let's say, even more... made with a even more sharp level of transparency.
[SPEAKER_00]: As to like, why am I doing these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're going to have to separate that from the fact that everybody around you is doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that has an influence as well on your values.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, well, it shouldn't, but that's the state you find yourself in.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that pretty much everybody around you is going the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eh... you kind of... you're trying to develop the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, for many people, that automatically... almost for everyone, that automatically makes it unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just having to go against what everybody else is doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you have that sutta that describes, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Other people will not be celibate, here we will be celibate, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Describes all these unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because in order to actually start taking that intention as the criteria, you will have to separate it from this collective sort of judgment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... that applies as a monk as well, because, you know, you could be in the monastic environment, just taking for granted that these things are good, not clarifying why.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in the lay life, it's like, it's more than just your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you can also be tempted to act out of stuff much more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you have to, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, keep the precepts, but then also stick to that recognition even more... to that questioning even more aggressively, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when people want to talk to you, let's say, it's not anything unwholesome, it's not anything sexual, it's not against the precepts, but are you delighting?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, do you catch yourself now, your mind, sort of like, you see that it has its own momentum, that it wants you to continue engaging in this conversation, regardless of what the practical reason for it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, see, all that peer pressure, all that kind of... the fact that those people don't even understand the practice that you're doing, and would completely think you're crazy if you try to explain it, all of that is going to pressure you even harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's going to make it even more difficult to say no in those situations.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you will have to, because the mind that you're training is the same, the defilements that you're abandoning is the same, and they certainly won't go anywhere if you're still giving in to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, they most certainly won't be weaker,
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're in an environment that breeds them even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's quite naive to think that you can do less work to get the same benefit, which is what a lot of people think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's basically what it boils down to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're gonna have to have an even higher level of self-transparency, because you have all these aids for covering things up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what about, like in lay life, you know, especially these days in the Western world, you have a kind of life of comfort, a lot of security, medical care, welfare state, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you say that that's in and of itself an obstacle to practice as a lay person, so that a lay person makes the environment more difficult or more uncomfortable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, see, if you think that the comfortable circumstances are in itself hindering you, then you again lose sight of what the delight is, what the craving is, what all the defilements are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say, practically speaking, for most people, there will be some level of dependence, actual emotional dependence on those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that is targeted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that they're depending on the entire scope of modern comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some of them, they may not actually care about all that much, even if they find it pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, the mind doesn't have that kind of compulsion and obsessive relationship with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you give those things up, just because they're comforts, and you sort of think that that will develop your mind, then that's self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's certainly not developing the criteria of what craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, it's more like you should be aware that those things are creating the gateway, like anything else, like the comforts that the Buddha had back in the day, which
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, there was also technology back then, relative to where people were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were things that were being introduced, that were not there before, and they felt like revolutionary or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could start becoming dependent on those, and taking safety in those.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more like you recognize that as a as a potential basis for delight, a potential basis for taking safety, but that doesn't mean you assume that just because it's comfortable, I'm already finding safety in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, if I remove it, I'm finding less safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, think about like what... see how your mind reacts to, let's say, the prospect of not having immediate access to medical care.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not you're gonna die or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like the prospect of it is slightly more distant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or let's say sometimes even not even medical care, like some people would even start freaking out even if they're... just because they're not able to eat more than one meal a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they know that it's not actually going to kill them, that they're eating enough calories, but it's still this irrational sort of need for something that is actually relatively or was relatively rare in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, you can see the dependence that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see the compulsion that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not just seeing, oh, this is comfortable, therefore it's bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seeing, my own mind, I can see how it feels threatened, if I... if... when I remove this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not abstract, like, just... just preemptively making that judgment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You actually see the... the sort of edge that starts to build up, if... if these things are even put under question, temporarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's what you want to start seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you want to see the actual obsessions that your mind has.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you start dealing with everything, even if you actually removed the things that were an issue, that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you're not developing the criteria and those dependencies will have moved on to something else, but now you think you dealt with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, that's when the Buddha described the craving as... it delights here and there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like it's, oh, this specific thing that always causes craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be left without senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And and everything that you previously would have depended on is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And still, as long as there is any consciousness, your mind will find something to latch on to, and you will think that it's not an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you projected the problem onto these external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, similarly, in the suttas, you have all these stories of how the ascetics would blame or think that the Buddha is not pure, because he eats all this fine food sometimes, and wears all these fine robes sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, it's like he gave the simile of... you have two people,
[SPEAKER_00]: One of them has the worst house, the worst food, the worst horses, the worst everything, but he can't give it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's dependent on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there's the other one who has the best house, the best horses, the best everything, but he gives it up overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, his mind doesn't have this obsessive relationship with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that other person is the one who actually succeeds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you could see, like, you could have all the modern comforts, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, it's not up to you, but, like, theoretically, it's not in those things, it's in that obsessive relationship that your mind has, the threat that it feels when it's removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that was the same with the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, he could have all these comfortable things, but, literally, overnight, he left the palace and then he had to sleep next to the side of the road, and then he was not bothered at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, see, it's not like... some ascetics would think, okay, so, why don't you just always sit on the side of the road then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, isn't that safer?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, no, because you're... if you're trying to remove things that are not a problem, as I said, you abandon the right gateway.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not looking at your intentions anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, precisely those people would have this... all these defilements underlying this external efforts to always be sleeping on the side of the road, always be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, all this greed and preferences and dependencies externally were replaced by this constant pressure to deny these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if those conditions are compromised, even accidentally, they feel hit with that arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind was dependent on that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though it wasn't unwholesome, it was just like, this was the thing that the mind latched on to now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, rather than trying to kind of do a general way of reducing the comfort or whatever...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the eight precepts already aim for most of the comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that removes the wrong... the types of comfort that are definitely wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ones that are definitely based on delight, definitely based on obsessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, try to establish yourself, or try to practice in the precepts as much as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you are kind of confident in that, then, rather than trying to reach a certain level of asceticism as a layperson, aim for the more specific things, that sometimes might be, sometimes might not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And stay on that ambiguous level of, like, the things that could be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, even if it feels
[SPEAKER_00]: riskier, that's the only place that you... that's... that's the only place where you can actually find safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, initially, when you're not developed in that perspective, it feels like kind of almost like unstable to... to just watch your intentions and not be worried about what it is externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's the other way around, because any issue could have only ever come because of that internal counterpart of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, it's like, it actually puts you in danger to be focused on the externals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, inevitably, you will let things through that should not have been let through, because you're not looking at the right gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the case of health care, if a person finds him or herself agitated by the thought of visiting or moving to a country and not having so much access to health care, what would be the right way to practice with that, when the mind resists the thought of not having easy access to health care, or no access at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, if you see the threat,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the scenario where, like, or you see how the mind feels threatened.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the scenario where exposing yourself to that discomfort could actually bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, that's the scenario where, for example, in the suttas, you would do the dūtanga, let's say, because you actually feel under threat if you don't have a roof over your head or if you sleep in an open space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, that creates that pressure, where you'll be able to now, let's say, more easily highlight, oh, this is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where I feel the arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where the kind of, like, as we were saying before, the impulse that underlies the unpleasant feeling, to respond to it, to sort of do something about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where you'll be able to
[SPEAKER_00]: Practice that perspective in regard to it, because, as I was saying before, that's what overcomes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, eh, you just do a series of steps, one, two, three, and then you hope for it to go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, any of that that you do is just going to be aiming at the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to be aiming at the mind's tendency when the unpleasant feeling arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to undo that tendency is to keep it in perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: To capture it, to keep it in check.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that you don't give it anything to latch on to, to sort of gain and keep absorbing momentum.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it fades.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you put yourself in the environment without health care, for example,
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, ideally, you should only do that type of thing when you already see your mind, because then you can be confident that you use it rightly, and won't just expose yourself to a risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you might die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you practice that perspective when those pressures are coming up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you will see, oh, actually, I managed to make this subside, the actual obsession compulsion behind it, and make it subside, while the the perception of the threat is completely unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I still know 100% that I might die, or might get sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that I just, again, explained it away, and like, oh, well, it's not really an issue, because blah blah blah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I still recognize this would be bad, and it would be nice to prevent it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, even if it happens, my mind will not be moved.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, there will not be that impulsive reaction to this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... and, of course, that will probably take a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like it's... because again, if you don't see your mind, you can sort of expose yourself to things and then slightly cover it up and then you overcome it for that reason, not because you actually dealt with the root of it, but you certainly have to be exposed to some level of challenge of that kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, if the precepts don't really, let's say, create any sort of internal... doesn't ruffle your feathers anymore, then, as I said, there surely has to be something else that you're dependent on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you go on to that, to sort of start seeing that mind more clearly, start seeing what the problem is more clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will know when it's enough, like when it's already kind of... it's coming up, it's challenging, I'm sort of slightly slipping into acting out of it, but it's not so much that I would just like just be completely overwhelmed and quit the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't necessarily mean as well that you straighten it where you need to move or go visit a third world country, but you could just deny yourself, like, taking an ibuprofen whenever you have a headache.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or doing all kinds of random check-ups with the doctor because it could be a one percent chance that you have... Yeah, or these little efforts to, like, optimize your health, that, like, again, are based on that pressure, based on that compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you refrain from that, and you just kind of stay with the thought of, oh, maybe I'll live 20 years less, because I didn't do this little, I don't know, special type of tea.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that brings up the pressure, and then you will have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what about questioning the underlying assumption of
[SPEAKER_01]: If I only have access to the right kind of medical care, or if I get the right check-up, if I get the right medicine, then everything will be all right, and I can start practicing, or everything is sorted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there seems to be an underlying assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just like the fear of pain, or displeasure, but a kind of underlying assumption that that is the solution to my suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, there is a... it is the aversion to displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just covers itself up in this kind of excuse that, oh, yeah, I need this because the health is so important for the practice and so on, which is true.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, what practice are you doing if you're acting out of craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, you do need it, but when it's tainted with that pressure,
[SPEAKER_00]: Necessarily, that's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That part is not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... that's what you have to keep an eye on, because... as you were saying before, one day it might be, like, completely fine, there's no pressure behind it, the next day it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that because, again, it's about health, it's automatically justified, or because it's about health, it's bad, because then I'm cultivating intoxication with health, automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, do I have the compulsion there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have the inability to say no to this and just kind of go to something else without the mind revolving around it?